<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cruelty of the magistrates of Evesham, in Worcester-shire, or, Some further particulars of their dealings and proceedings at the late sessions, and othertimes, against those people, whom scornfully they call Quakers with a warning to the heads and rulers and all people of this nation / written from Evesham the 15 day of the 8 month, 1655.</title>
            <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12278535</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12278535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58576</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1515:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cruelty of the magistrates of Evesham, in Worcester-shire, or, Some further particulars of their dealings and proceedings at the late sessions, and othertimes, against those people, whom scornfully they call Quakers with a warning to the heads and rulers and all people of this nation / written from Evesham the 15 day of the 8 month, 1655.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Smith.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58576:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58576:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CRUELTY OF THE MAGISTRATES OF <hi>Evesham,</hi> in <hi>Worceſter-Shire,</hi> OR, Some further particulars of their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and proceedings at the late Seſſions, and othertimes, againſt thoſe <hi>People,</hi> whom ſcornfully they call QVAKERS. With a Warning to the HEADS and RVLERS and all people of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Written from <hi>Eveſham</hi> the 15. day of the 8. Month, 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle,</hi> neer the west end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58576:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58576:2"/>
            <head>The Crueltie of the <hi>Magistrates</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſham</hi> in <hi>Werceſterſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>UPon the nineth day of <hi>September</hi> ſo called, we had a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the tenth hour, at the common Goal in <hi>Eveſham,</hi> there to wait upon the Lord, and after ſome time <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> having been in priſon about three weeks before, and being in the priſon, he was moved to ſpeak to the Lord in prayer, then the Goaler, and ſome other Officers came into the Goal to <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey Smith,</hi> and violently haled him away as he was ſpeaking to the Lord in prayer, and put him down into the dungeon; our friends keeping ſtil together, after ſome time <hi>Tho. Woodrove</hi> ſpake the word of the Lord to the people, and having done, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable came and inquired for him, but becauſe they knew him not, he went away that time; but before they departed, another mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was appointed the third hour in the afternoon, and then the people being come together at the time appointed, <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> ſpake to his friends out of the Dungeon the word of the Lord; and when the common Meeting at the Steeplehouſe was ended, our friend <hi>Thomas Woodrove</hi> was ſpeaking to the people, without the priſon, and many of thoſe that had been at the ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plehouſe ſtood and heard him ſpeak, who having done ſpeaking, was ſought after, and took away by a Conſtable without a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and brought him before the Mayor, and them called Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and <hi>Thomas Mathew</hi> Prieſt, and then he was committed to the common Goal for ſpeaking the word of the Lord, and <hi>Sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mathew</hi> Prieſt, at his departure thanked the Mayor for his care and pains, and on the morrow in the morning, <hi>Robert Martin,</hi> called Juſtice, bid the Wardſmen, if t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e people would not bee gone from the goal-hole, he bid them knock them down, and bid the men throw ſhuffles ful of dirt upon them in the dungeon; and they ſet eight men with weapons, four on each ſide the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to keep away all friends for coming to, or ſpeaking with them they had impriſoned; <hi>Humphrey</hi> being free to give books to ſome people of the Country there in town, and the keeper did
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58576:3"/> by violence take three books from them, and tore them all; ſo he ſent for a parcel of books he had in town about ſixty in number, which was for the glory of God, &amp; for the beating down of all ſin, written by <hi>George Fox, Iames Naylor, Richard Farnſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> and <hi>Iames Parnel,</hi> theſe books they were taken from the meſſenger by the wardſmen, and brought before the Iuſtices, who afterwards burned them upon the Market-Croſs before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being the Fair-day; ſee their malice to them, having broke no Law, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.54. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.13,14,15. &amp; <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.10,11. <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.2,3,4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.4. to the 16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29 17. This was done, notwithſtanding that ſome of our friends did preſent the Mayor the firſt day in the morning with a paper that had above forty hands a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, declaring that they expected juſtice to be put in execution according to the late Proclamation, which they denyed to poſt up, though ſome friends poſted it up, and it was pulled down again; they onely bear the names of Juſtices, and do it not, but their actions are ſecretly contrary to law, juſtice, and righteouſneſs, and they are thoſe that call the proud happy, yea by their means thoſe that do wickedly are even ſet up, and delivered, and they lay ſnares for the righteous, and make a prey of thoſe that fear the Lord, whoſe faces are now turned towards Zion, lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their fore-fathers, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.25: <hi>Act.</hi> 22.24,25. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.12,13. &amp; <hi>Act.</hi> 24.5,6,9. <hi>Act.</hi> 25.2,3,4, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.17,18. Upon the 25 day of the 7 moneth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led September, <hi>George Kemp,</hi> Mayor of Eveſham, ſent for us priſoners, and more of friends in the town, and ſaid, I ſent for you concerning a paper that you have put your hands to, beeing <hi>A repreſentation of the Government of</hi> Eveſham.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Do you own this paper?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, we do own it, and ſhall prove it to be all truth. He then began to queſtion ſome particular things in it to inſnare us, but after we urged very much, he granted the reading of it, then he examined us that were there, but all that were wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the paper, were not then in the town; we bid him let us be called all together, and we ſhal prove every thing therein; then ſaid he, ſeeing it is of ſo high concernment, and that you have appealed to the Protector, you ſhall every one give ſecurity to anſwer it before the Protector.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We have not appealed to the Protector, for any redreſs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58576:3"/> but we have diſcharged our conſciences in making manifeſt the corruption of them called Magiſtrates in this Town, both to the Protector and to the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest</hi> Are you willing to anſwer it before him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If we be by you or the reſt compelled, we refuſe not to go, for we are more free to anſwer it before the Protector than here, for there we expect ſome Juſtice, but here is none. I ſhall engage you all to appear at the Seſſions, and then you ſhall all give ſecurity to anſwer perſonally before Protector, or elſe lye in Priſon. What is the reaſon you will not ſwear, <hi>William Dewſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry</hi> can ſwear, for in one of his books he ſaith, in the preſence of the Lord I own Magiſtrates: <hi>Hum. Smith.</hi> So far as that I can ſay, for in the preſence of the Lord I own Magiſtrates that are for the praiſe of them that do wel, &amp; the puniſhing of the evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: So he lets us that were Priſoners return to the Priſon, and the reſt departed home.</p>
               <p>Upon the 28. day of the Month, called September, <hi>Joſhua Fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> and <hi>Iobn Knight</hi> was ſent for before them called Juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es, Robert Martin, and Samuel Garner, and asked them if they owned the printed paper, they ſaid we own it, and can prove it all to be true; them called Iuſtices ſaid it was a Lybell, they anſwered they would prove it was no Lybell by thoſe twenty that are ſubſcribed in print to that paper, which they queſtioned them about, and alſo by forty more; The Deputy-Recorder ſaid whether it be true or falſe it is a Lybell, becauſe it is in diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the Magiſtrates; ſo them called Iuſtices ſent them both to Priſon: At that time there was in the place, one <hi>Thomas Milnard,</hi> the Prieſts wife father, who was a perſecutor in the Biſhops dayes, he is one of them called Magiſtrates, he accuſed our friends of ſelling their Bibles, he mentioned one of Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, who though he did ſell a Bible hath two or three yet, and the Scriptures we own, yet I can ſell thee a Bible, if thou wilt buy one, for I have three. <hi>Thomas Milnard</hi> anſwered, I will have none of thy Witchery ſtuff, he ſaid more, that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that the Mayor was bewitched he did not ſend all our friends to Priſon that 25. day of the 9. Month Ioſhua Frenſome, Iohn Knight.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58576:4"/>
               <p>On the ſecond of the eight moneth called October, Iames Wall having a tryal at their Court, he came into the trial of the cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and Robert Atkins commanded his hat to bee taken off, Iames Wall ſaid to him, Thou haſt not yet made me any ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the laſt hat thou cauſeſt to be taken from me, neither is yet reſtored; Robert Atkins commanded the Goaler to take him to priſon, where he hath been without any <hi>Mittimus</hi> or any thing ſince laid to his charge.</p>
               <p>The ſecond of the ſaid moneth, at the Seſſions holden at E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſham, Thomas Woodrove being firſt ſent for, by himſelf, and brought before the Seſſions, he requeſted that his fellow priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners might be ſent for, that they might anſwer to the crimes laid againſt them, if there were any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> You are accuſed to be a diſturber of the peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Let that be proved, or read any Law that I have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iudge.</hi> There may be a Law broken which cannot be read.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is it poſſible there ſhould be Law broken that cannot be proved nor read?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> But as for your part you might have had your liberty if you had not came in here in this contemptible way, with your Hat on, therefore you ſhall turn back again to the Priſon, until you do come with your hat off; take him Goaler. He was ſent to the priſon, and the reſt brought up to the Bar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Atkins</hi> ſaid, Do you not know that you are priſoners? I marvel that you wil offer to come before a Court with your hats on; Goaler take off their hats. It was done: thou maiſt as wel take off our Coats.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iames Wall.</hi> Thou haſt not made me any ſatisfaction for the laſt hat thou did cauſe to be taken from me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. Atkins</hi> ſaid, <hi>Smith,</hi> You are the Ring-Leader of this Sect, and of this people; I know you have Scripture enough, and you can tell of <hi>Pauls</hi> Condition, and many ſuch things, but you lead people contrary to the wayes of God.</p>
               <p>Humph: Smith. <hi>Paul</hi> was accounted as a Sectarian and a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Sedition, and a peſtilent Fellow</p>
               <p>Rob. Atkins. Paul was called ſo, but was not ſo; but you are called ſo, and are ſo.</p>
               <p>Anſ. That is not yet proved:</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58576:4"/>
               <p>Rob: Atkins. Where have you any Scripture for your keeping on your hats.</p>
               <p>Tho. Cartwright. The ſervants of the Lord had their Hats on when they were thrown into the Fiery Furnace, yet they were not thrown in for keeping their hats on, but becauſe they would not bow and worſhip the Kings Image.</p>
               <p>Humphrey Smith. There is neither precept, practiſe, exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor command in the ſcripture, nor yet any Nationall Law for putting off the hat, and ſo long as I continued in ſwearing, lying, and in other wickedneſs, I was never queſtioned by any magiſtrate, but now the Lord hath called me from theſe Sins, I am made a prey of by you; then ſaid they one to another, he hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed all the magiſtrates in England: <hi>Queſt.</hi> Did you live in ſuch Sins ſince you came to this Town? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nay, <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> ſaid, I have lived in drunkenneſs, ſwearing, lying, and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, until now of late, and none of you ever queſtioned me, but now I have left it I am puniſhed without a cauſe: if any one here have ought againſt me now to charge me withall, let him now ſpeak before the people. <hi>Rob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tkins.</hi> Thou lookeſt with a good honeſt face, I thought thou had not been a quaker, therefore I thought to have ſhown the ſome favour, but I ſee by thy beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iour who thou art; <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> ſaid, <hi>Moſes</hi> that was a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, did look with a better face then he. <hi>Robert Atkins:</hi> Here is a ſufficient ground, that you have come into the Court with your hats on, to fine you, and ſend you to Priſon untill you learn bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manners, therefore I ſhall fine you every one and ſend you to Priſon, where you ſhall lye from one Seſſions til another, untill you come with your hats off, if I may have my will; and though you have been kept very high, J ſhall take courſe that you ſhall be kept ſhorter, and looked cloſer unto, fine ſuch in five pounds and the reſt in three pounds a peece, Goaler take them away; the Goaler hawling us away, <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> ſaid, let it firſt be made manifeſt who we have offended, or what we have tranſgreſſed, or what errors J hold, if any can be proved, that the peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> may be convinced with us of any evill we may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of, but the Goaler hawling us away <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> ſpoke further to the people, and ſaid, they have ſhamed all profeſſion, and all nationall Government: Thus were we thruſt away from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58576:5"/> the bar in a quarter of an hours time, and not at all called by name nor examined for what we were Priſoners, nor any Mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus read or mentioned, nor any other crime laid againſt us, or charged upon us, neither was any Witneſs, nor any one by word or bill, that had any thing in the leaſt againſt us, neither did any open his mouth to that purpoſe, or in any ſuch way againſt us, neither did they themſelves accuſe us, though we often reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to ſhew us any cauſe why we were impriſoned, but the Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler took four of us away, but <hi>Robert Smith, Iohn Clemens</hi> and <hi>Sames Wall</hi> he left at the bar, where they then ſpake for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; <hi>Robert Atkins</hi> hearing them, asked if they were quakers too, and called the Sergeants, or Words men to take them away, but they were let alone untill the Goaler came back again from the Priſon, in all which time they were not examined, neither did any one accuſe them of any thing. <hi>Rob. Smith</hi> ſaid he had been in Priſon 6. weeks for ſaying the Prieſt did lye; now there the Prieſt, <hi>George Hopkins</hi> is, and I am here to prove him a lyar, and to affirm him to be a lyar before all the Court, if he be not a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar let him ſpeak, for I can prove him a lyar in ſeverall things; the Prieſt being there gave no anſwer. <hi>John Clemens</hi> ſaid I was ſent for by the Deputy-Recorder (who ſitteth there) from my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhop and his work, and he ſent me to Priſon becauſe I did not put off my hat, and for that have I been in priſon 6. weeks, and he called to the Deputy-Recorder, and bid him ſpeake or charge him with what he had againſt him, but he was ſilent, and ſpoke not, neither did any one charge him with any thing; ſo when the Goaler came, he took them away to priſon alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A true deſcription of the impriſonment of <hi>William Pit,</hi> a ſouldier for the Commonwealth.</head>
               <p>I Came from my outward being in the City of <hi>Worcester,</hi> into the Burrough of <hi>Eveſham,</hi> to viſit ſome friends which were there in Priſon for bearing witneſs to the truth, as it is in Jeſus being the time of the Generall Seſſions for the ſaid Burrough and coming into the Hall on the third of the 8th. Month, and was walking with many of my friends in the lower end of the Hall, below the Bars and the people, until there came a man with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58576:5"/> a Halbard, and carried me before thoſe which ſate to do juſtice (but J found none) whereupon the Recorder told me, he did perceive J had a deſire to be amongſt my fellows, and I ſhould, have my deſire, I bid him do his pleaſure, but J demanded him firſt to make it appear I had tranſgreſſed either the Law of God or man, but he could not, then he asked me what I came hither for from my dwelling place; my anſwer was, I came to ſee the Tryall of my friends which are here in bonds for the teſtimony of Ieſus, and I am chargeable to no man; ſo with ſome other queſtions of ſmall account, he bid take him Goaler, ſo I bid him let me know what he ſent me to Priſon for, but he would not, but ſent me to the Common-Goa!, without any Mittimus or knowledge of my perſon or name, or whence I came, neither wil they let me know for what, although I have writ to the Mayor.</p>
               <p>The third of the Month, called October, <hi>Ioſhua Frencom,</hi> and <hi>John knight,</hi> Priſoners, were ſent for unto the hall, and after <hi>Robert Atkins</hi> had commanded to take off their hats, which were accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, he then cauſed a Bil of indictment againſt them to be read, concerning ſom particulars in a former printed paper, &amp; asked if they were guilty or not guilty; <hi>Joſhua</hi> anſwered, we can bring witneſs to prove that to be true, which we are indicted for; <hi>Rob. Atkins:</hi> Wherefore are you indicted? <hi>Joſh.</hi> For the truth. <hi>Rob. Atk.</hi> For the truth are you indicted? <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſaid, All people take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, for the Truth it is that we are indicted; and the people clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their hands, gave a ſhout, and ſome of them ſaid to <hi>Rob. Atkins,</hi> let ſhame cover thy face, muſt not men ſpeak the truth? <hi>Rob. Atk.</hi> Take them away, for we ſhall not have peace ſo long as they are here; on the ſame day, before mentioned, <hi>Rich. Walker</hi> was called, and they read a bill of indictment againſt him, and they asked him whether he was guilty or no; and he ſaid he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the bill, but ſaid he owned the paper, and he deſired to have it read, and they did, and when it was read, he ſaid, I appeal to all your conſciences, whether it be not all true, and they ſate all ſilent, and anſwered not a word. <hi>Iohn Woodard, Iames Wall, Ioſhua Frencom, Thomas Cartwright,</hi> and <hi>Will. Walker,</hi> were ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers long in the ſervice of the Commonwealth, and moſt of them at Worceſter fight for outward liberty, and now are they fined, or impriſoned, or both, without any Law tranſgreſſed, and are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58576:6"/> deprived of outward liberty: <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> was a friend to the Parliaments Army, from the firſt arſing of them, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ventured his naturall life, and ſuffered much loſs by the kings army, and now we have not the leaſt benefit of the liberty nor law of the Nation. Upon the third of the 8th. Month, <hi>Iohn Goodard</hi> was called before the bench, <hi>Rob. Atkins</hi> ſaid, pluck off his hat, and after his hat was off, the Town-clerk did read ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp; ſaid in his paper that he had ſet his hand to a ſcandalous paper maliciouſly againſt the magiſtrates of the town, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards asked him if he was guilty or not guilty, and he ſaid he was not guilty of wronging any mans perſon, neither had he ſpight or malice againſt any man in England, and the Recorder ſaid, it is eaſie for any man to ſay he is not malicious; and the ſaid <hi>Iohn Goodard</hi> ſaid, thou maiſt judge of me what thou wilt; and then Robert Atkins ſaid, will you own the paper? And he anſwered that he would own the printed paper; and prove it to be true; and ſaid, here are three men ſtanding by, that have waited ever ſince yeſterday morning, to witneſs againſt Robert Martine, called Iuſtice, for ſwearing: Robert Atkins ſaid he did not ſit there to have it proved; and ſaid, if it were true it ought not to be ſpoke of if it were againſt a Magiſtrate; and Iohn Woodward ſaid, all people take notice if this be not partiality: (The Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der commanded that Captain Pit wayes hat to be taken off his head, which is a Magiſtrate of the Town, and makes him ſtand bare, and ſuffers a prieſt to ſit by him with his hat on; and the Prieſt hearing this put off his hat, and the Recorder bid him put it on again, and yet he ſends our friends to priſon for coming before him with their hats on.) And then the Recorder ſaid to the reſt of the Bench fine him; and ſome of them ſaid three pounds; and they asked the ſaid Iohn Woodward if he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, and he ſaid, you may do what you will with me; and the Recorder ſaid, fine him five pounds: &amp; he ſaid you may put in fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pounds, for I expect no favour from your hands; ſo they fined him five pounds. And Iohn Woodard ſaid, Take notice the Grand Iury have brought in, that ſwearers and drunkards are not puniſhed; and ſaid, Hear people, We are not queſtioned for ſweating nor being drunk, or any manner of ſin, or evill commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, but for ſpeaking the truth: and one of the ſtrangers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58576:6"/> ſaid, I witneſs againſt Robert Martine for ſwearing, and they did not anſwer him a word:</p>
               <p>Upon the ſecond day of the 8th. Month, called October, our Friend, Captain Pitway, ſo called, was called before the Bench; and Robert Atkins, the Recorder, ſaid to him, I underſtand that you have been a Magiſtrate, and one of the chiefeſt of the Bench, and I do much admire that you ſhow no more reverence to the Court then to come with your hat on, [mark reader,] and now a ring-leader of this ſect, I will take courſe with you; and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to this purpoſe, I ſee little juſtice done: and then <hi>Atkins</hi> ſaid, you ſhall ſee juſtice done, and ſaid, pluck off his hat, that is one piece of juſtice; then <hi>Atkins</hi> ſaid, you are bound over to your Good Behaviour, and then it was read what was ſworn againſt him, and that which was falſe in it he denyed, and that which was true in it he owned; and then Robert Atkins bid him relate what he did own, and he ſaid that he owned that the ſaid Robert Martine, called Iuſtice, was a drunkard: and becauſe he did pluck the priſoners out of their beds, and bred ſuch a diſturbance in the night, and bidding the people whoop, and whooping him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he ſaid did cauſe him to ſay what he ſaid, and ſaid if they would but give him leave to bring in his witneſſes, he would prove it to be true; and then he bad him bring in his witneſſes on the morrow: then the recorder did tell him of a paper that he had put his hand to, which was ſcandalous againſt the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the town, and he ſaid he put his hand to a paper which was no ſcandall but truth, and he was there ready to prove it to be true, and then for that time he was put by, and the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning about the ninth hour, he was then called again, and then they read an Indictment againſt him, for ſetting his hand to a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which they ſaid was maliciouſly againſt the Magiſtrates, and asked him if he owned it; and he ſaid, all malice and ſpight I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but for the printed paper he owned it to be true, and was there ready to prove it: and Robert Atkins ſaid, we conceive it to be ſcandalous, and would not ſuffer him to call his Witneſſes, and ſaid, We muſt proceed to fine, and ſo fined him 20. l.</p>
               <p>The 14th. Day of October, being the firſt day of the Week, there vvas a meeting at Captain <hi>Edward Pitwaye</hi>'s houſe, in the morning, and there vvere tvvo of our friends coming to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58576:7"/> meeting, and as they paſſed by the Goale they looked in at the the Goal hole, and ſpake to the priſoners, and before they had ſtayed half a quarter of an hour, there came the Mayor and put them in priſon, and ſaid they ſhould go into the priſon right or vvrong: and in the afternoon, <hi>Edward Young,</hi> the Mayor, came to our meeting before the Goal, vvhere our friend, Humphrey Smith, ſpake out of the Goal-hole, and the Mayor came and laid violent hands of many of our friends, and ſent them avvay to priſon, and ſeveral Country people he ſet in the Stocks, although vve vvere all peaceable, and not a man did give him, or his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables that vvas vvith him, a vvord that vvas uncivill, but deſired that vve might be peaceable in our meeting, but the Mayor vvas very outragious, and one he did kick, and another he did lay hands on, and ſaid, he had almoſt forgotten the civil Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſo ſent him to priſon, and did put our friend, <hi>Humphrey Smith,</hi> and the reſt that were in the Main-Goal into the Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſaid we ſhould not ſee his face again, it may be, this twelve months, except he had order from above to take him out; and ſome Women he laid hands on and plucked them, and ſaid if he had a priſon for them they ſhould go to Priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>TO all the Heads and Rulers of this Nation, and Great men, and Rich men, who would have the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> put off to you; and would have your perſons reſpected, which is contrary to the Law of God, for he that reſpecteth perſons committeth ſin, and he is a tranſgreſſor of the Law of God; and you that ſay authority commands it, and would have your perſons reſpected, you that do ſo commit ſin, and would have others to commit ſin, and ſo to tranſgreſs the Law of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and to depart from the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is without reſpect of perſons, which faith is held in a pure conſcience, which all who reſpect perſons acts contrary to that which doth convince them, and caſts the Law of God behind their backs, and are reprobates concerning the Faith of our Lord Jeſus: When <hi>Haman</hi> would have had <hi>Mordicai</hi> to have bowed to him, when he could not diſobey the Law of God, <hi>Haman</hi> might ſay he diſobeyed, and was not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58576:7"/> ſubject to authority, as you do now, when men ſtands patiently by you, which ſay authority commands it to put off the hat, who would have the creature worſhipped more than the Creator, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch the judgements of God comes: as you may read, <hi>Rom:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And as the three Children could not bow to the Image which Nebuchadnezar had ſet up, they might ſay they diſobeyed au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and was not ſubject to authority, as you may do now, becauſe men do not off their hats in your Seſſions and Courts, and ſo they come to be fined, which there is no example for in all the Law of God, but it is a judge upon all that reſpect perſons to which the ſoul muſt be ſubject. And all who follows the luſts acts contrary to the Light which doth convince, there that is let in which wars againſt the ſoul; he that makes Laws and acts in that nature, and with it, which follows the luſts, and ſets up that which wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s againſt the ſoul, which the ſoul cannot be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to, but to the higher power, that which anſwers the Law of God, and the higher power is that which doth convince, which the ſoul muſt be ſubiect to, and not to mans will, neither to that which is made in it, nor to that which doth command, for the croſs is to it, and ſo all you which would have hats put off to you ſeeing there is not one example among all the heatheniſh Kings or rulers as you read in all the Scriptures: and all you who hath &amp; doth profeſs the Scripture to be your rule, ſearch it throughout, and ſee if you can find any example in it, that ever any that were rulers for God that commanded any to put off their hats to them; and if you cannot, you may ſee you are grown higher in iniquity, pride and ambition than them all: Nebuchadnezar loſt his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; &amp; <hi>Haman &amp; Pharoah</hi> deſtroyed, who oppreſſed the ſeed, of God. And beware all ye that ſcoff &amp; ſcorn, &amp; perſecute the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeed of God, the power of God is the ſame now that it vvas then to throvv you dovvn, and that of God in all conſciences ſhall anſvver it. And you vvho profeſs your ſelves Chriſtians and Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and the Scriptures to be your rule, ſearch it, and ſee if you can find any example among all the Saints of God, or any of the Chriſtian Magiſtrates that did beare rule for God, command any to put of their hats to them: Did ever Moſes, Ioſhua, or Iephtha, Solomon, or Hezekiah, vvho vvere Iudges and Kings in Iſrael, command any to put off their hats that came
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58576:8"/> before them? Or did any of theſe impriſon them? if they did not, or ever <hi>Pharoah, Herod, Pilate, Darius,</hi> or <hi>Foelex,</hi> or any of the heatheniſh Kings or Governours command any to put off their hats that came before them, or fine them, or impriſon them, if they did not; now ſeeing none of theſe commanded any to do it, what can you plead for it but your own wills? and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how you make that your Law, as you will anſwer it, for you muſt all give an account to the juſt God of heaven and earth, who will tender to every man according to his works, without reſpect of perſons. From the Lord I warn you, and to the Light in all conſciences I ſpeak, that with it you may ſee the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ruling in you that ruled in Haman, who would have had Mordecai to have bowed down to have ſatisfied his will, which he would not do though the King had commanded it, and he was juſtified by God in not doing of it; and Haman, who would have been honoured, brought to ſhame and confuſion. Read Eaſt. 2.7 10. Therefore all ye Rulers, fear the living God, and give over perſecuting the Saints, which cannot reſpect your perſons for Conſcience ſake, for the Lord God of Heaven and Earth wil be avenged of all his Adverſaries, and upon all the oppreſſors of his own people, that would make them tranſgreſs the righteous Law of God, which reſpects no mans perſon, and you that do ſo are enemies to God, and ſo denies the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is without reſpect of perſons, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. With the Light of Chriſt you are all ſeen, and with the Light you are to be condemned, you that act contrary to it, for this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, the Light, ſaith Chriſt; as you may read, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19,20,21. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>AND now all you that are called Magiſtrates, in Eveſham, who are yet in the murderous nature, hating, perſecuting, and reviling the innocent whom you cannot iuſtly accuſe, this have I written that you may look back and be aſhamed of all your former filthy actions, which have been contrary to all that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58576:8"/> ever ruled for God, therefore now minde that of God in your Conſciences, which will witneſs for me, and iudge and condemn your unjuſt actings, which have been contrary to the righteous Law of God in your heart, and alſo to all the Laws in the nation; and thou, <hi>George Kemp,</hi> when thou didſt examine us, theſe, or the like words I then ſpake &amp; now write to thee, that thou, or any other, to ſhow, if they can, what Law I, or <hi>Thomas Cartwright,</hi> had tranſgreſſed, or who we had harmed, or what uncivill carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, words, or actions, we had offered to any man; yet a Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble came and took us before them called Magiſtrates, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice that we that are called <hi>Quakers</hi> would not ſwear, nor put off our hats to worſhip the Beaſt in any man, but uſe plainneſs of ſpeech to all, by which we are made a prey of, ſo are many enſnared when there is no other way found out to intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them that cannot bow to your generation, that are found fighters againſt the Lord. And thou <hi>Robert Atkins</hi> Recorder, and the reſt that joyned and ſate with thee at the Aſſizes in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting of the Saints, even of thoſe that have alwayes had their outward habitations in the ſame town, and none of you, nor any other adverſaries could then charge them with any thing of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion or evill behaviour towards any, yet you fined many, and ſent them to priſon, and fined them in ſums of money for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before you with their hats on, and declaring againſt your fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy actions in a printed paper, wherein your former actions are truly declared, as fiftie of us can witneſs, and that in your own conſciences may witneſs the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now are you made manifeſt and ſeen in the Light, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all the ſimple, to be ſuch who are out of the counſell of God, acting in your own wills, to your own ſhame; are theſe your actions? the fruits of your Miniſtry you are upholding? do you thus requite the Lord for his Deliverance from the outward Sword? Are you now leading into Captivity, and ſet wholly to perſecute and to delight your ſelves in miſchief? Now hear and conſider, all ye rulers of the earth, that ſet your ſelves in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel againſt the Lord; Thus in the day of his power wherein he is ariſing, yea the Lord of Hoſts is riſen to take vengeance againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u his enemies, and to break you all like a Potters Vessel; yea, the wrath of the Lord of Hoſts is kindled, which burns all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58576:9"/> day, and his jealouſie is waxed hot againſt you, and his wrath you ſhall not eſcape; the day of the wrath of the Almighty is at hand, wherein he is raining, and will rain ſnares upon the wicked day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the wicked ſhall be taken in their own craftineſs, and ſhal howle and lament for all your abomination, for the Lord is coming a ſwift witneſs againſt all proud, lofty and ſcornful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, who live in covetous practiſes, whoredomes, and the like: Wo unto them that take counſell, but not of me, ſaith the Lord; Wo unto you that go down to Egypt for help; Wo unto you that decree unrighteous decrees; Wo unto you that lay ſnares for the innocent, the judgements of the living God are your portions for ever if you repent not ſpeedily: Oh! repent, repent; return, return before it be too late, that you may not all utterly be deſtroyed for ever, for by you the juſt upright man is laughed to ſcorn, and judgement is turned away backwards, and juſtice ſtandeth afar off, truth falleth in the Streets, and equity cannot enter, and he that departeth from evill maketh himſelf a prey; but the Lord loveth the righteous, and he knoweth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked afar off, for on them he will rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone and horrible tempeſts, this ſhall be the portion of your cup Wo unto you that call evill good, and good evill; that put darkneſs for Light, and Light for darkneſs. Wo unto you that are wiſe in your own eyes, and prudent in your own ſight. Wo unto you that are mighty to drink wine, and men of ſtrength to pour down ſtrong drink; which juſtifie the wicked for rewards, and caſt the innocent into holes, as the fire devoureth the ſtubble, and the flame conſumeth the chaff, ſo your Root ſhall be rottenneſs, and your bloſſome fade as the duſt, becauſe you have caſt the Law of the Lord behinde your back, yea, the Lord will render to every one of you, in one day, according to the evill of your heart, and what meaſure you have meaſured to us, ſhal be meaſured to you again, and the Lord in his good time he wil deliver us out of the hands of the wicked and unreaſonable men, which make a man an offender for a word, and the time will come when you ſhall know that you have been fighters againſt God, and have been perſecutors of the righteous ſeed of God, which are in ſcorn cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers: Therefore all people, both Judges and Rulers, high and low, while you have time priſe it, and repent from all your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58576:9"/> dead works and ſerve the living God now in this the day of your viſitation, for there is no darkneſs nor ſhadow of death where you workers of iniquity may hide your ſelves from the preſence of our God, who is a conſuming fire, before whom all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall vaniſh like ſmoak, and howle, becauſe of the torment that is coming upon all that are found in Babell, out of which the Lord hath called many of us up into the Marriage of the Lamb, where vve rejoyce over Babylon that is fallen, and all that are found in her, from vvhom vve are delivered to offer up prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and honour, and obedience unto the living God of povver, vvho ſitteth on the Throne, To him be given glory and honour for ever and ever, Rev. 19.1,2,3,4,5. and the 18.20:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>NOvv a word in love to all people, to warn you every one to minde your own condition, and ceaſe from the buſie mind, that goeth forth from the light of Chriſt in thee, to meddle with other mens matters, and ſo give way to the adulterated ſpirit in thee, that is adulterated from the Lord, and ſo the feet abides not in the houſe, but followeth after that which entreth forth after that which ſaith, Lo here, and lo there, and ſo mindeth not the Priſoner vvithin thee, vvhich groaneth for deliverance, and cries for vengeance upon the head of the vvicked one in thee, vvhich bears rule and leadeth thee from obedience of what is made manifeſt to thee by the Light of Chriſt, to go forth feeding upon the Tree of Knowledge, where thou wouldſt be as God, knowing good and evill. But to that in thy conſcience do I ſpeak thou knoweſt enough already to be thy condemnation, for the Light of Chriſt is come into the worldly heart, which ſheweth thee ſin, and evill, and wickedneſs is thy condemnation, becauſe thou loveſt thy own unfruitfull works rather than the Light which ſheweth thee it; therefore ſaith the Lord, the people have choſen their own ways, and delighting themſelves in acting that which was not good, and have gone a whoring after their own inventions, and will have none of me, but caſts my Law behind
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58576:10"/> their backs, and rejects my counſell, and abhor my correction, and receive not the fear of the Lord, although I have ſent my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets, riſing up early, and ſending them to cry in the ſtreets, the chief places at Concourſe, at the entring in of the Gates, and in the high places, ſaying unto all, O do not this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable thing which I hate: and this voice doth alſo call in thee, ſaying, this is the way, walk in it, when thou art turning to the right hand or to the left; and yet the <hi>Lord</hi> hath long waited to be gracious, and to heal thy back-ſlidings, and love thee freely, but thou turneſt to him thy back and not thy face: O ye rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous children! How long will you delight your ſelves in miſchie? and how long wil you walk in a way that is not good? How long wil you hold the truth of God in unrighteouſneſs? O people! will you nor be made clean? When ſhall it once be? How long wil you follow after the falſe Teachers that are gone forth from <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> &amp; the <hi>Truth,</hi> into the world? who have eyes full of <hi>Adultery,</hi> with the Spirit that is adulterated from the <hi>Lord:</hi> Hearts, have they, exerciſed with covetous practiſes, and ſuch that are greedy after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for rewards: Theſe are they that cannot ceaſe from ſin, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14, but have a <hi>form</hi> without the <hi>power,</hi> and from ſuch turn away: and mind the <hi>light</hi> of Chriſt the true <hi>teacher,</hi> &amp; the true <hi>Light</hi> that ſheweth <hi>ſin</hi> &amp; <hi>evill;</hi> when no man can accuſe thee, yet the <hi>Light</hi> will then condemn thy unjuſt practiſes, and check thee in ſecret for <hi>ſwearing, lying cozening,</hi> and the like; this is the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which appeareth, unto all men, which teacheth to deny all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs,</hi> and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>luſts,</hi> which all they that are <hi>Chriſts</hi> have crucified with the affections; who are become dead unto <hi>ſin</hi> and alive unto <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and then how can theſe that are dead unto <hi>ſin</hi> live any longer therein? for the <hi>wages</hi> of ſin are <hi>death,</hi> and he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth ſin is the ſervant of ſin, and whileſt we were with you committing ſin, we were free from <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> but being now made free from <hi>Sin</hi> by the clenſing of his <hi>Blood,</hi> we became the <hi>Servants</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſs:</hi> Therefore all you that are yet the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>Corruption,</hi> mind your condition, <hi>his ſecvants you ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to whom you obey, whether of ſin unto death, or of righteouſneſs unto life, and not one of you can ſerve two Maſters, therefore be no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iued, God will not be mocked any longer by you:</hi> if you continue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58576:10"/> ſowing to the fleſh thou ſhalt as certainly of the fleſh reap <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> therefore all ye that are reader<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and not obſervers, and hearers of the Word and not doers, you are all deceived, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. the <hi>ſwearer, lyar, drunkard, hater, proud, covetous</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>ſcorner</hi> are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived already, none of all theſe ever comes to enter into the Kingdom of God, until he be brought out of their deceit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Serpent hath deceived all the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>wrath,</hi> for no unclean thing ever enters into the Kingdome of <hi>God,</hi> which is <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>joy,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And all you that are condemning thoſe that perſecuted the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned them; and you that are condemning thoſe for perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting impriſoning, and crucifying <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and are ſaying, if you had been in the dayes of your forefathers, you would not have perſecuted the <hi>Saints</hi> as they did, and yet in the mean time you your ſelves are in the ſame nature as they were, and the Works of your fathers that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vv the <hi>Prophets</hi> you vvill do, for this day are you perſecuting the <hi>righteous Seed,</hi> that ever ſuffered under your <hi>Generation priſons, Stocks, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngeons,</hi> yea death it ſelf: Therefore hear and conſider; Did ever the ſervants of <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> cauſe any to be impriſoned? Or did they ever ſtrike, ſtone, hate or revile any? Did they ever make uſe of any <hi>Nationall law,</hi> made by the will of man, to enſnare any? Or ever havvle any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore earthly <hi>Magistrates?</hi> Therefore conſider, you that are laying ſnares for the innocent, and are havvling them to priſon that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bovv to <hi>Hamans</hi> nature nor yours, that Heatheniſh cuſtome of putting off the Hat, and that cannot ſvvear, but abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.33,34. And them that do not break the lavvs of God or man, are dayly caſt into priſon, and great ſums of Money impoſed upon them by the Wil of proud man; Are not the great men of the earth taking counſell againſt the Lord, and againſt his Annointed? Is not <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> agreed to crucifie Chriſt in his Members? Are not the chiefe Prieſts and Rulers joyning together novv as they did? <hi>Act.</hi> 24. Are not many moved vvith envy? Are not the rulers novv ſeeking for ſomthing againſt thoſe they can finde nothing vvorthie of death or of bonds? like that of <hi>Act.</hi> 25.25,26. Is there not like tumult raiſed by the ſvvearing rude Multitude, as vvas <hi>Act.</hi> 17.5? Are not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſaying as they did of Chriſt, one ſaid he is a good man, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58576:11"/> other ſaid nay, but he deceiveth the people, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.12. Are not the great ones of the earth ſometimes ſaying now, as a certain Orator ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> (that was not made a Miniſter by the will of man) that he was a Peſtilent fellow, a mover of Sedition, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of Nazarites? <hi>Act.</hi> 24.5. Are there not many <hi>Hamans</hi> now, that would have the true <hi>Mordecaies</hi> to bow to them, and becauſe they wil not, all their glory in the world availeth them nothing, and therefore are ever ſaying of thoſe who are Jews indeed, as it is ſaid of the Jews <hi>East.</hi> 3. that they are a certain up-ſtart-people ſcattered abroad, which regards not the <hi>Kings laws,</hi> neither are they for the <hi>Kings</hi> profit? And would not many <hi>Hamans</hi> in England give large Money if they might prevail to have the righteous cut off for ever out of the Nation? as it was <hi>East.</hi> 3. Nay, are not you more blind and worſe perſecutors than they were, either in the dayes of the prophets or Apoſtles, who then ſpake the word of the Lord as they were moved from the mouth of the Lord, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. and they had not a Scripture to prove it by, yet you blame them that caſt them into Priſon? Now we ſpeak plain Scripture, and write plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (which you ſay is your Rule) and we ſpeak nothing, neither do we act or uphold any thing but what is declared by plain Scripture, yet are impriſoned therefore: Are you not worſe than your forefathers. Now <hi>Daniel</hi> was put in the Den, becauſe, ſay they, he hath broke the Kings command in praying, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. But I was put in the Dungeon and there kept ten dayes onely for praying and making ſupplications to the living God, and in it I did not break any Nationall Law, therefore are ye not worſe than your fathers? Again, they might have charged <hi>Paul</hi> with preaching contrarie to the Scriptures, for he ſaith if they were circumciſed Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. and yet Circumciſion was a command of God to laſt in <hi>Israel</hi> for ever. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.13,14. and <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf was circumciſed, yet the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward circumciſion <hi>Paul</hi> preached againſt, therefore <hi>Paul</hi> was perſecuted; but we now having ſo far a Declaration written <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. from thoſe holy men of God, who ſpoke forth the Scripture from the ſame Spirit, Chriſt the Light of the world, that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world was, in which <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, <hi>Noah</hi> preached and obeyed, <hi>Arbaham</hi> believed before the Scripture
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58576:11"/> was, in the which, <hi>Moses</hi> the man of God ſaw and writ the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was many hundred years before his naturall birth; in the ſame the Prophets ſtood and propheſied of Chriſt to be the Light of the Gentiles, and of them that ſit in darkneſs, Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6. &amp; 9.1. who came to fulfil that which was ſpoken of him by the Prophets, from the ſame light and life which dwelt in him, Col. 1.19 in the which the Apoſtles preached, in which we alſo preach repentance to the world, as Chriſt the Light of the world did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4,17. <hi>Mark</hi> 1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3 4. And we ſay from the ſame ſpirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the righteous; it ſhall go well with them, Iſa. 3.10,11: Mal: 3:18: which is according to the Scripture, and ſo we ſpeak the truth of God, which your ſelves holds forth in words, but you live in untighteouſneſs: <hi>Rom:</hi> 4:18:</p>
               <p>Therefore all people leave off your wickedneſs, and turn to the living God, <hi>who ſo loved the world, that he gave his only Son.</hi> Rom. 5. the light of the world which world is ſet in mans heart, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 3:11. of which Chriſt is the inlightner, the which whoſo followeth, ſhall not walk in darkneſs, but ſhal have the light of life, Iohn 8:12: Now why wil you love the unfruitful works of darkneſs? why wil you go on in your wickedneſs? Do you not know, that the wicked ſhal do wickedly, and none of the wicked ſhal eſcape, and that the unrighteous cannot inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, 1 Cor 6:9: and that the Lord wil in no wiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the wicked, Exod: 34:1: but wil wound the head of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the hairy ſcalp of every one that goeth on in iniquity, Pſa. 69.21. Now in the light of Chriſt thou mayſt read thy porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the wicked, which ſhall be turned into hell, as they that forget God, and caſt his righteous Law behind their backs, and trample the blood of the innocent under their feet, and turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, fooliſh jeſting, corrupt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, vain jangling, idle words, the fooliſh heart being ful of laughter, it is the ſport of a fool to do miſchief, the God of the world having blinded the eye, the Prince of the power of the ayr beareth rule in all the children of diſobedience; Therefore all ye ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets and Apoſtles have ſaid, you fooliſh people without underſtanding, that have eyes but ſee not, and ears that hear not, fear ye not mee, ſaith the Lord? wil you not tremble at my preſence? Ier. 5.21,22.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58576:12"/> which is terrible unto all the workers of iniquity, who are now committing iniquity with greedineſs, drinking it downe as the Oxe drinketh water, heaping up wrath againſt the day of wrath, and righteous judgments of God, which are now revealing from heaven upon all manner of unrighteouſneſs of men, Rom. 1. wherein in this day of the revelation of Ieſus Chriſt, all that do wickedly ſhal be as ſtubble before him that ſits as a Refiners fire, Mat. 3.2,3. and is coming a ſwift witneſs againſt his Adverſaries: therefore all people conſider your wayes, ſee what you are a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for none can eſcape the wrath at hand, whither can you go? whither can you fly? where can you hide your ſelves from the preſence of the Lord? who is come to call for an account for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very idle word, all unrighteouſneſs is ſin, that which he will not ſuffer to go unpuniſhed; therefore whileſt you are called to day Oh! harden not your hearts any longer; let not your words be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>out againſt the Lord any more; let the wicked forſake his ways, and own the light of Ieſus Chriſt, while it now ſhineth, leaſt the Lord cauſe darkneſs, and thy feet ſtumble for ever at the dark mountains, Ier: 13.16 and ſo thou come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be for ever ſhut ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into utter darkneſs, where there is no recovery; <hi>therefore give ear a little, hear and thy ſoul ſhal live: Deſpiſe not the day of thy viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; hear, for wiſdome cries, and underſtanding puts forth her voice, yea, ſhe ſpeaketh excellent things,</hi> Prov. 8 <hi>Oh ye ſimple, turn you in hither, and yee fools be ye of an underſtanding heart, why wil yee die, Oh ye houſe of</hi> Iſrael! <hi>ſeeing I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth: turn yee again, and ye ſhal live; go on, and yee ſhal dye the death eternally: Therefore if thou haſt any love to thy own ſoule, that is more worth then the whole world, mind thy condition, flatter thy ſelf no longer between God and Mammon, thou canſt not ſerve two Maſters, while thou ſerveſt thy own will, which is above the Croſs, thou art contrary to the fathers wil, which is, that all men ſhould be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth as it is in</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>who is the Saviour of the ſoul, and the teſtimony of</hi> Ieſus <hi>is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpirit of propheſy,</hi> Rev. 19.10. <hi>which sheweth things to come,</hi> Iohn 16 13. <hi>whereby the ſecrets of the</hi> Lord <hi>are revealed to us that fear him,</hi> Amos 3.7. Pſa. 25.14 <hi>and the minde of Chriſt comes to be known<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (1 Cor. 2.16.) <hi>unto the ſpiritual man that judgeth all things, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he himſelf is judged of no man,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. <hi>for</hi> Chriſt <hi>the ſonne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58576:12"/> righteouſneſs is raiſed up in him, Mal.</hi> 4.2. <hi>where the ſon bears rule, unto whom all judgment is committed, Ioh.</hi> 5.22. <hi>by whom now the</hi> Saints <hi>do judg the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.2,3. <hi>that keepeth in wickedneſs, therefore</hi> I <hi>witneſs againſt all the world, that the works thereof are evil,</hi> Io 1:1 <hi>fer in the world the dogs and the euil workers are, who are all diſc. ouered in the light of</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>From them that are priſoners for the truth; that are by the dark world called Quakers, whoſe names in the fleſh are, <hi>Humprey Smith,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Woodrove.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
